Guide to the Frank Traver De Vyver Papers, 1899-1980 UA.29.02.0161
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Frank Traver De Vyver papers
1899-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
De Vyver, Frank Traver, 1904-1980
UA.29.02.0161
27 Linear Feet
Frank Traver De Vyver, 1904-1980, was an economist, professor of economics, and university administrator at Duke University from 1936-1980, and Vice-President of Erwin Cotton Mills from 1945-1955. The Frank Traver De Vyver Papers, 1899-1980, comprise the correspondence, writings, research, administrative and managerial records, and other professional papers of the economist Frank Traver De Vyver, who was a scholar on the history of labor economics and labor movements and unions. The collection is arranged in six series. Correspondence and Personal Papers contain his personal and professional correspondence and biographical material, including a photograph album of his travel abroad and a scrapbook of his career. The Writings and Research Series contains drafts and reprints of his articles and his research on labor unions and industrial arbitration in Australia and the United States. The Department of Economics Series mainly consists of departmental correspondence and administrative records. De Vyver's work as a Duke University administrator is documented in the University Committees Series, with the largest groups of materials being from the University Planning Committee and the Educational Facilities Committee. The Subject Files cover all of De Vyver's professional activities, including his work as a professional arbitrator for the American Arbitration Association; his managerial career as Vice-President of Erwin Cotton Mills, Durham, N.C.; his service on government committees and boards, including the War Production Board; his scholarly work on labor economics and industrial relations, collective bargaining agreements, grievance procedures, wages, and textile workers; documents on the Textile Workers Union of America; and his work on the history of labor movements and labor unions in the United States, Australia, and South Africa. The Printed Materials Series contains reprints of his articles and a variety of other formats, including clippings, pamphlets, posters, and serials.
15,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
Records, such as search committee files or others pertaining to employment where individuals are identified, are closed for 70 years.
Provenance
The Frank Traver De Vyver Papers were received by the University Archives and the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer and gift, 1966-2010.
Biographical and Historical Note
Chronology
1904 May 14 Born, Mount Vernon, N.Y.
1926 A.B., Oberlin College
1927 M.A., Oberlin College
1930 M.A., Princeton University
1930 Published Labor in the Industrial South, with Abraham Berglund and G. T. Starnes
1935 Ph.D., Princeton University
1935-1974 Instructor, Assistant Professor, and Professor of Economics, Duke University
1940-1957 Director of Undergraduate Students, Department of Economics, Duke University
1945-1955 Vice-President, Erwin Mills, Durham, N.C.
1946 Published Development of Economic Society, with George Modlin
1956-1957 Fulbright Lecturer, University of Sydney
1957-1964 Chairman, Department of Economics, Duke University
1962-1969 Vice-Provost, Duke University
1964 Fulbright Lecturer, University of Western Australia
1978 July 1 Appointed University Distinguished Service Professor Emeritus, Duke University
1980 May 11 Died, London, England
Collection Overview
The Frank Traver De Vyver Papers, 1899-1980, comprise the correspondence, writings, research, administrative and managerial records, and other professional papers that De Vyver produced in a half-century career as an economist and scholar specializing in the history of labor economics, movements, and unions, as a professor of economics and a university administrator at Duke University, and as an industrial manager and arbitrator. De Vyver's papers have been arranged in the following six series. The Correspondence and Personal Papers Series primarily consists of his personal and professional correspondence, but also contains biographical material, including a photograph album of his travel abroad and a scrapbook of clippings, photographs, and printed materials about his professional career. The Writings and Research Series contains drafts and reprints of De Vyver's articles and his notes and research materials on such topics as the history of labor unions and industrial arbitration in Australia and the United States. De Vyver's writings are followed by the Department of Economics Series, which includes some teaching materials but is mainly composed of departmental correspondence and administrative records. In addition to his teaching and departmental duties, De Vyver was also very active in the administrative life of Duke University, and this part of his career is extensively documented in the University Committees Series. His work on more than twenty committees, councils, and task forces is represented here, with the largest groups of materials deriving from the University Planning Committee and one of its standing committees, Educational Facilities, which De Vyver chaired from 1962-1974. The Subject Files make up the largest series, comprising almost half the collection. These files cover the full breadth of De Vyver's professional life, not only complementing topics covered in other series but also documenting many colleagues, organizations, and subjects not represented elsewhere in the collection. The following are among the most prominent groups of materials in the Subject Files: De Vyver's work as a professional arbitrator, generally as a representative of the American Arbitration Association; his managerial career as a Vice-President of Erwin Cotton Mills, a textile mile formerly in Durham, N.C.; his service on various government committees and boards, including the War Production Board; his scholarly work on and professional involvement with a wide variety of subjects and organizations in the fields of labor economics and industrial relations, including collective bargaining agreements, grievance procedures, wages, and textile workers; materials about the Textile Workers Union of America; and the history of labor movements and labor unions in the United States, Australia, and South Africa. The final series of the collection consists of Printed Materials, including reprints of De Vyver's articles and a wide variety of loose research materials in such categories as clippings, pamphlets, posters, and serials.
Photograph albums; Scrapbooks; Labor unions -- South Africa -- History; Labor unions -- United States -- History; Textile workers -- Labor unions -- Southern States -- History -- 20th century; Wages -- Textile workers -- North Carolina; Arbitration, Industrial -- Australia; Labor movement -- United States -- History; Labor unions; Labor unions -- Australia -- History; Collective labor agreements -- United States; Economics; Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Collective bargaining; Economists -- United States; Clippings (information artifacts); Grievance procedures; Economics -- Study and teaching -- North Carolina -- Durham; Economists -- Correspondence; Labor economics; Industrial management -- History; Industrial relations; Duke University. Department of Economics; Duke University -- History; Duke University. University Planning Committee; Duke University. Educational Facilities Committee; De Vyver, Frank Traver, 1904-1980; De Vyver, Frank Traver, 1904-1980; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University -- Administration; American Arbitration Association; Textile Workers Union of America; Erwin Cotton Mills; United States. War Production Board
- Correspondence and Personal Papers Series, 1904, 1926-1980 and undated, 3 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Primarily personal and professional correspondence, with a small amount of other personal information, including biographical details, awards, clippings, vitae, travel, and a few miscellaneous financial documents. Correspondence is arranged chronologically, followed by personal information folders at the end of the series. A photograph album and scrapbook, described below, are boxed separately.
  - Correspondence, 1937-1980, 14 folders (Box 1)
  - Ashe County property, 1955-1971 (Box 1)
  - Biographical, personal, and financial information, 1904, 1958-1980 and undated (Box 1)
  - Calendar, business cards, and loose materials, 1972-1973 and undated (Box 1)
  - Photograph album, 1950s-1960s (Box 19)
    Photograph album documenting one or more overseas trips and cruises by the De Vyvers. Places pictured include sites in the Caribbean islands, Copenhagen, London, and Paris, and many unidentified locations. Contains approximately 450 black-and-white and color prints and post cards. Undated, circa late 1950s-early 1960s.
  - Scrapbook, 1926-1980 (Box 20)
    Chronological scrapbook of De Vyver's career and personal life, from his student years at Oberlin and Princeton through the bulk of his career at Duke University. Contains awards, clippings, correspondence, photographs, programs, and reprints of several of his earliest published articles. Many loose items inserted in the album have been removed and foldered separately.
- Writings and Research Series, 1934-1973, 3 boxes
  Drafts and reprints of articles, notes and card files, printed items, and other research materials for De Vyver's writings. A large proportion of the material dates to the 1950s and 1960s and concerns his extensive work on labor and management issues in Australia, but the series also contains his research on various African countries, articles he published as Vice-President of Erwin Mills, and a hand-corrected typescript of his doctoral dissertation. Arranged in alphabetical order, by title or general subject area.
  - Africa--correspondence, drafts, notes, and reprints of articles on Kenya, South Africa, and other countries, 1953-1960, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Australia--miscellaneous research on New South Wales and Queensland, 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - Australia Public Service Board--correspondence, printed material, and research notes, 1952-1969, Folders 1-4 of 8 (Box 1)
  - Australia Public Service Board--correspondence, printed material, and research notes, 1952-1969, Folders 5-8 of 8 (Box 2)
  - Australian sugar industry--correspondence and printed material, 1954-1957, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Broken Hill mining industry (Australia)--article, notes, and printed material, 1953-1969, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Collective Bargaining: Diffusion of the Concept in English-Speaking Countries (1968)--article and drafts, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Employers' Associations Developments (1972)--article, correspondence, and drafts, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Government Control of the Internal Affairs of Trade Unions: Australia and the United States (1972)--article, correspondence, and drafts, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Industrial Relations Policies in Australia, typescript of article, circa 1973 (Box 2)
  - The Melbourne Building Industry Agreement (1959) and The Melbourne Building Industry Agreement: a Re-Examination (1970)--articles and notes, 1955-1970, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Metal trades--correspondence, research notes, and printed material, 1952-1957, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - National Labor Relations Board, 1947-1949 (Box 3)
  - New Zealand--award to clothing trades employees, 1954-1957 (Box 3)
  - The 1920 Civil Service and Teachers' Strike in Western Australia (1965)--article and research materials, 1920-1965, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - The Organization of Labor in New Jersey before 1860, edited typescript and manuscript of dissertation, Princeton University, 1934, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Pointers for Supervisors, 1950-1953 (Box 3)
    Typescripts and clippings of a regular column De Vyver wrote for the magazine Textile World when he was Vice President and Director for Personnel Relations, Erwin Mills.
  - Reviews and short articles by De Vyver, 1947-1972 (Box 3)
  - Section 28 Disputes, typescript of article and notes, circa 1957 (Box 3)
  - The Weakening of Managerial Rights (1959)--article, correspondence, drafts, and notes, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - Untitled card file--notes from North Carolina newspapers and state publications, 1880s-1930s (Box 3)
- Department of Economics Series, 1925-1980, 1 box
  Correspondence, bylaws, budgets, newsletters, and other files of the Department of Economics and the Department of Economics and Business Administration. Although material covers the full duration of De Vyver's career, approximately half of it dates to the years 1957-1964, when he served as Department Chair. There is also some very early correspondence about department faculty members in the 1920s and 1930s. Arranged alphabetically by topic, chronologically within larger categories.
  - Alumni--correspondence, news, mailings, 1976-1980 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1925-1944
    This small group of correspondence probably originated in the files of William Henry Glasson, Professor of Economics from 1902-1940 and Dean of the Graduate School of Arts and Science, 1926-1938. In part, the letters document the recruitment and first years at Duke of several early members of the Economics Department faculty.
    - General correspondence, 1925-1941 (Box 4)
    - Earl J. Hamilton, 1927-1944 (Box 4)
    - Christopher Roberts, 1929-1940 (Box 4)
    - Ben Lemert, 1930-1937 (Box 4)
    - John Troxell, 1932-1938 (Box 4)
    - Frank T. De Vyver, 1934-1937 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1957 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1965, 9 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 4)
  - Department by-laws, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Departmental meetings, 1953-1963 (Box 4)
  - Exams and keys, 1971-1974 (Box 4)
  - Graduate program--committees and reports, 1957-1967 (Box 4)
  - Graduate students correspondence--general, 1963-1979 (Box 4)
  - Graduate students correspondence--references and admissions, 1962-1975, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - "Graduate Study in Economics," 1921-1968 (Box 4)
  - Memoranda, reports, and general information, 1957-1980 (Box 4)
  - National Science Foundation--grant application to remodel Building 10 for Research in Economics, 1962-1965, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Newsletters, 1958-1978 (Box 4)
  - Paul Gross dinner, 1959 (Box 4)
- University Committees Series, 1938-1974, 4 boxes
  Correspondence, memoranda, minutes, reports, and printed materials from approximately two dozen committees De Vyver served on or chaired at Duke University. Several of the longer-term committees are represented by their own collections in the University Archives, and these related materials are noted in the folder entries below. Arranged in alphabetical order, as received.
  - Closed materials from University committees (Box 5)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Materials in Box 5 contain minutes of the Buildings and Grounds Committee of the Duke University Board of Trustees, closed for fifty years from date of creation; and documents from two University committees that refer to named individuals' employment records, closed for seventy years from date of creation.
    - Building and Grounds Committee of the Duke University Board of Trustees, 1965-1969 (Box 5)
    - Employee Relations Advisory Committee, 1968-1969, 3 folders (Box 5)
      Includes information on USME Local 77.
    - Personnel Policy Committee--Unions and related correspondence 1965-1968, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Administrative Council, 1961-1969, 3 folders (Box 6)
    Includes records produced under the Council's earlier name, "Administrative Committee" (circa 1961-1963); also, other related materials can be found under both names in various collections in the Duke University Archives.
  - African Studies Committee, 1965-1969 (Box 6)
  - Committee on Retiring Faculty, 1945-1949 (Box 6)
  - Computer Planning Committee, Executive Subcommittee, 1968-1969, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Computer Planning Committee, Executive Subcommittee: Freeman Task Force on the Establishment of the University Computing Center in the Old Chemistry building, 1969 (Box 6)
  - Contracts, Grants, and Related Personnel Committee, 1961-1964, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Council on Gerontology, 1955-1956 (Box 6)
  - Curriculum, Standing Committee on, 1938-1951, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Duke Fund correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 6)
  - Duke University development campaign (faculty committee), 1950-1951 (Box 6)
  - Educational Administration Committee, 1960-1969, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Educational Facilities Committee, 1960-1974
    De Vyver chaired this standing committee of the University Long-Range Planning Committee from 1962-1974. For related materials in the Duke University Archives, see also the Educational Facilities Committee Records, 1962-1986.
    - General files, 1960-1972, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Minutes, 1963-1974, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Space, 1963-1972 (Box 6)
    - Subcommittee on the Woman's College Physical Education Facilities, 1962-1970 (Box 6)
    - Subcommittee on the University Center, 1964-1965 (Box 7)
  - Faculty Club Committee, undated (Box 7)
  - Faculty Health Program Committee, 1946-1949 (Box 7)
  - Faculty-Student Advisory System Committee, 1942, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Inter-University Committee for Economic Research on the South, 1960-1965 (Box 7)
  - Nursing Education Committee, 1964-1969, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Personnel Policy Committee, 1965-1968, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - Provost's Group on Retirement Policy, 1963-1970 (Box 7)
  - Psychological Services Task Force, 1972-1974 (Box 7)
  - University Council, 1952-1962, 3 folders (Box 7)
    Related materials in Duke University Archives include the University Council Records, 1952-1962.
  - University Planning Committee, 1962-1968, Folders 1-8 of 14 (Box 7)
    Materials include general files, minutes, and information about this committee's related successors, the University Policy Advisory Committee (UPAC) and the University Policy and Planning Advisory Committee (UPPAC). Related collections in Duke University Archives include the University Planning Committee Records, 1962-1973, and the records of the UPC's predecessor, the University Committee on Long Range Planning, 1958-1962. Some materials from De Vyver accession UA 93-96 were previously transferred to the latter collection.
  - University Planning Committee, 1962-1968, Folders 9-14 of 14 (Box 8)
- Subject Files, 1899-1980, 9 boxes
  Materials include correspondence, articles, clippings, collective bargaining agreements, committee minutes, company records, research grants and studies, photographs, project files, and printed materials. Prominent people, organizations, and topics include Australia, Duke faculty response to the Gross-Edens matter, Erwin Cotton Mills, the Federal Advisory Council, Douglas Knight, labor-management relations, South Africa, and the War Production Board. Arranged in alphabetical order, as received, with loose and unsorted materials filed at the end.
  - Symposium on Aging and Social Policy, 1964-1966 (Box 8)
  - Socio-Economic Studies of Aging, 1962-1968 (Box 8)
  - Alumni Affairs, 1960-1969 (Box 8)
  - Alumni speech--1969 Feb. 26 (Lexington, KY), 1966-1969 (Box 8)
  - Your University--alumni meeting--1965 Sept. 26 (Marshville, NC), 1965 (Box 8)
  - Alumni speeches, 1966-1969 (Box 8)
  - American Labor Movement--A Brief History, by the U.S. Department of Labor, 1948 (Box 8)
  - American Research Institute in Turkey, 1965 (Box 8)
  - Arbitration, 1920-1980, 43 folders
    - Acme Boot Company, 1965-1967 (Box 8)
    - Agreement Between Erwin Mills, Inc. and Textile Workers Union of America (TWUA), 1950 Oct. 11 (Box 8)
    - Albemarle Paper Company and United Papermakers and Paperworkers (UPP), Local 425, 1966, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Arbitration cases--general, 1963-1967 (Box 8)
    - Arbitrations, 1942, 1958-1962 (Box 8)
    - Borden Manufacturing Company, 1963, 1965 (Box 8)
    - Charisma Chair Company and Upholsterers' International Union of North America, Local 320, 1975-1977 (Box 8)
    - City of Memphis Hospital and American Federation of State, County, and Municipal Employees, 1976-1978 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 8)
    - Dayco Arbitration Panel, 1963-1964 (Box 8)
    - Duke Power Company, 1961-1962, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Erwin Cotton Mills Company, 1942 (Box 8)
    - Erwin Mills, Inc., 1947, 1954-1958 (Box 8)
    - Florida Light and Power Company, 1960-1964, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - General files and clippings, 1942, 1951-1953, 1980 (Box 8)
    - General Telephone Company of Florida, 1972-1974 (Box 8)
    - General Tire and Rubber Company, 1970-1980, 7 folders (Box 9)
    - Georgia Power Company and International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers (IBEW), 1960-1977, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Great Atlantic and Pacific Tea Company and the Retail Store Employees Union, Local 876, AFL-CIO, 1971-1973 (Box 9)
    - Hoerner Waldorf Division of Champion International Corporation and United Paperworkers International Union (UPIU), Local 425, 1979 (Box 9)
    - J.P. Stevens Co., Inc. vs. National Labor Relations Board and TWUA, AFL-CIO, 1963-1967, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Jim Robbins Seat Belt Company, 1972-1973 (Box 9)
    - The Mead Corporation and United Mine Workers of America (UMWA), 1959-1960 (Box 9)
    - Memphis and Shelby County Hospital Authority, 1972-1973 (Box 9)
    - Memphis Park Commission, 1974-1975 (Box 9)
    - Mohawk Rubber Company and United Rubber, Cork, Linoleum, and Plastic Workers of America (URCLPWA), Local 1023, 1980 (Box 9)
    - Niemand Industries, Inc., 1965, 1974-1975 (Box 9)
    - Paper on arbitration, 1941-1942, 1960-1961, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Rose Hill Poultry Company, 1965-1966 (Box 9)
    - Stein-Hall Southern, Inc. and RWDSU, Local 15-A, 1972-1973 (Box 9)
    - Union Camp Corporation and UPIU, Local 783, 1976-1979 (Box 9)
    - Westinghouse Electric Corporation and United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 3130, 1978-1979 (Box 10)
    - West Virginia Pulp and Paper Company, 1920, 1955-1959 (Box 10)
    - Weyerhaeuser Company New Bern, NC and United Paperworkers, Local 220, 1970-1973 (Box 10)
  - Australia, 1956-1975 (Box 10)
  - Australia--Fulbright grant, 1955-1956 (Box 10)
  - Automation: Effects on Labor Force, Attitudes, and Skills, by Herbert R. Northrup, 1958 Aug. 20 (Box 10)
  - Australian Conciliation and Arbitration System, 1970-1971 (Box 10)
  - Automotive and Aviation Parts Manufacturers, Inc.--Memo to Management by Frank Rising, 1945 Nov. 21 (Box 10)
  - Baruch Project, 1963 (Box 10)
  - Beall, Larry, 1973 (Box 10)
  - Bevan, William--Committee on Pacific-Asian Studies, 1979 (Box 10)
  - Black, M.L. Jr., 1930-1938 (Box 10)
  - Blackburn, John O., 1958-1963 (Box 10)
  - Reprint Bulletin--book reviews by Professor de Vyver, 1973-1978 (Box 10)
  - California conference, 1940 (Box 10)
  - Chamber of Commerce of the United States--Dependents Allowances Under State Unemployment Compensation Laws, 1947 (Box 10)
  - Clark, Robert L., 1974-1975 (Box 10)
  - Coleman, John J.--The North Carolina Paradox: Organized Labor's Encounters with the Law in North Carolina, 1900-1930, 1978 Mar. 3 (Box 10)
  - Collective Bargaining, 1944-1951 (Box 10)